{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This action was supported by Eduardo Frei’s Christian Democratic Party and occurred after sweeping gains for one leader’s party in midterm elections. The target of this event gave a radio broadcast that he ended with the words “Long live the people! Long live the workers!”, then used a gold-plated AK-47 to commit suicide while barricaded in La Moneda Palace. For ten points, name this event that led to the rise of the military dictator Augusto Pinochet.",
      "answer": [
        "overthrow of Salvador Allende",
        "death of Salvador Allende",
        "descriptions of a coup d’etat against Salvador Allende",
        "descriptions of the 1973 Chile coup d’etat",
        "descriptions of “the coup d’etat that brought Augusto Pinochet to power” before his name is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the 1971 edition of this game, success was determined by how fast and accurately they typed words like “BANG” or “WOW.” MECC produced this game, in which taking the Barlow Road or floating across the Columbia River Gorge are the two options for players as they approach Willamette Valley. The player is responsible for leading for leading a wagon party starting at Independence, Missouri in, for ten points, what classic educational computer game that shares its name with a pioneer route?",
      "answer": "The Oregon Trail"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician issued a namesake Moratorium in an attempt to give Germany more time to catch up on reparation payments. In another postwar role, this man organized Belgian food relief efforts. The Smoot-Hawley Tariff was signed by this man, who promised “a chicken in every pot” during his presidential campaign. As unemployment peaked, shantytowns became named for, for ten points, what president who led the US into the Great Depression?",
      "answer": "Herbert Hoover"
    },
    {
      "question": "This medium was created by Otto von Guericke’s Magdeburg hemispheres, a demonstration of the strength of air pressure. Inverting a barometer onto a dish of mercury proved to Torricelli that this medium was created when internal and external atmospheric pressure reached equilibrium. Leucippus’s atomic theory, which argued that all particles move in this medium, countered Parmenides’s claim that “nature abhors” this state. For ten points, give this term for a space that does not contain matter.",
      "answer": "vacuum"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was appointed king by Mongol ruler Sartaq Khan and died shortly after traveling to Sarai to pay tribute. This man thwarted Hermann of Dorpat from capturing Pskov during a battle in which the lake Peipus had frozen over. Before that battle against the Teutonic Knights, this man rose to fame defending Novgorod against the Swedes. For ten points, name this ruler of Kiev known for a victory on Lake Peipus at the Battle of the Ice.",
      "answer": "Alexander Nevsky"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s DusitD2 hotel and office complex was targeted in a January 2019 terrorist attack that killed 21 people in the Westlands neighborhood. In the same neighborhood in 2013, over 60 people were killed and 200 wounded in a similar attack, also carried out by members of al-Shabaab, at this city’s Westgate shopping mall. In August 1998, Al-Qaida bombed the US embassies in Dar es Salaam and, for ten points, what capital city of Kenya?",
      "answer": "Nairobi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Edward Larson wrote a history of this election year titled A Magnificent Catastrophe. William Freehling claims that the Three-Fifths clause was central to the incumbent’s loss in this election year, whose winner gave a diplomatic inaugural address in which he claimed “We are all Republicans, we are all Federalists.” A Federalist supported a rival in this election year by claiming he was “by far not so dangerous a man” as Aaron Burr. Alexander Hamilton played a crucial role in, for ten points, what election year in which Thomas Jefferson replaced John Adams as President?",
      "answer": "US Presidential election of 1800"
    },
    {
      "question": "Inthis US state, Augustus Stinchfield partneredwith a British man toform a private medical practice. Miners flocked to this state following a discovery in its Vermilion Range. Charles Alfred Pillsbury founded his namesake company in this state, where its flour mills competed with rival General Mills. Iron ore from mountains in this state was transported by train to cities like Duluth. The Mayo Clinic was founded in Rochester in, for ten points, what US state where 3M is headquartered in a suburb of St. Paul?",
      "answer": "Minnesota"
    },
    {
      "question": "Resistance against Nazi occupation in this city was led by an organization whose logo was the letters “PW” in the shape of an anchor, the AK or Home Army. Mikhail Tukhachevsky was defeated outside this city by Jozef Pilsudski in the “Miracle on the Vistula.” The Z.O.B. led a revolt in this city that was defeated by Jurgen Stroop, after which most of the Jewish Combat Association was deported to Treblinka. For ten points, name this city whose ghetto underwent a major revolt in 1943 in Poland.",
      "answer": "Warsaw or Warszawa"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a battle during this campaign, the USS Choctaw was hit more than fifty times without suffering any casualties. This campaign included the Battle of Snyder’s Bluff and a battle where troops marching up Rodney Road were attacked by the forces of John Bowen, the Battle of Port Gibson. This campaign’s most famous battle ended with the surrender of John Pemberton on July 4th. The Army of the Tennessee fought in, for ten points, what Grant-led Union campaign named for a Mississippi city that was besieged in 1863?",
      "answer": "Vicksburg Campaign"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Members of this denomination practice the Arba’een pilgrimage, which is the largest religious gathering on earth, in the city of Karbala. That pilgrimage takes place forty days after a holiday on which this denomination mourns the death of Husayn, the day of Ashura. This denomination includes the Sevener and Twelver sub-sects. For ten points, name this denomination of Islam, the majority in Iran and the second largest after Sunni.",
        "answer": [
          "Shia Islam or Shiites",
          "or Shias"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shias believe that this man, rather than Abu Bakr, is the rightful successor to Muhummad and the first Imam.",
        "answer": "Ali ibn Abi Talib"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began when one side took a stand a Mozhaysk, refusing to follow Barclay de Tolly’s advice to retreat. Utitsa village was burned to the ground after it exchanged hands multiple times in this battle. The losing side in this battle sought to defend the Raevsky redoubt. After defeating Mikhail Kutuzov, this battle’s victors entered Moscow, only to find it empty. For ten points, name this 1812 victory for Napoleon on Russian soil.",
        "answer": "Battle of Borodino"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This fictional man observes, then participates in, the Battle of Borodino in an 1869 novel. This character later decides to try to assassinate Napoleon and later marries Natasha Rostova.",
        "answer": [
          "Pierre Bezhukov",
          "either",
          "both names"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Frank Lloyd Wright influenced one of the earliest buildings made with this material, Robert van’t Hoff’s Villa Henny in Utrecht. This material was used in the construction of 146 nearly-identical apartments that were built for the 1967 World’s Fair; that prefabricated housing complex designed by Moshe Safdie, Habitat 67, is a famous example of Brutalist architecture. Romans constructed the Pantheon’s dome with the “unreinforced” type of, for ten points, what building material that binds gravel or stones with cement?",
        "answer": "reinforced concrete"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Concrete was also heavily used by this architect, who was commissioned by Jawaharlal Nehru to redesign Chandigarh, India. The Villa Savoye embodies this man’s “five points” of architecture.",
        "answer": "Le Corbusier"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This modern state was home to a colony where Thomas Morton brewed beer and erected a maypole for a multiracial population, Merry Mount. Mary Dyer was executed in this modern state, where the Antinomian Controversy in this state was begun by Anne Hutchinson. Cotton Mather presided over a series of trials in this state that began with the accusation of the Barbadian slave Tituba. For ten points, name this modern state in which the Salem Witch Trials took place.",
        "answer": "Massachusetts"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Morton wrote a letter describing this militia captain at Plymouth, noting that this man cut down his maypole. This signer of the Mayflower Compact was called “Captain Littlesworth” and “Captain Shrimpe” due to his small stature.",
        "answer": "Miles Standish"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A refusal to recognize this country was maintained in the Hallstein Doctrine until the Basic Treaty normalized relations. The Monday Demonstrations led to the downfall of one of this country’s leaders. Its leaders included Egon Krenz, Erich Honecker, and Walter Ulbricht, and its secret police under Marcus Wolf closely collaborated with the KGB. For ten points, name this country that constructed the Berlin Wall to bar migration to its western neighbor.",
        "answer": [
          "East Germany or the German Democratic Republic",
          "Deutsche Demokratische Republik"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The division and administration of Germany after World War II was determined in August 1945 at a meeting in this city.",
        "answer": "Potsdam"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man briefly retired to Caprera, an island he partially owned, after he was wounded and captured at the Battle of Aspromonte. This former schoolmaster worked for the Republic of Rio Grande do Sul in his early career, granting him the nickname “hero of two worlds.” This man was victorious at the Battle of the Volturnus, which came near the end of his Expedition of the Thousand. For ten points, name this commander of the Redshirts, a hero of Italian unification.",
        "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Expedition of the Thousand ended in February 1861 at the Siege of Gaeta, where this king surrendered, ending the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. The last Holy Roman Emperor shares this king’s name and number.",
        "answer": "Francis II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Forces of this dynasty won the Battle of Liaoluo Bay over Dutch East India Company ships by using fireships. During this dynasty’s Jiaqing Emperor, Wokou pirate raids intensified, and despite earlier passing the Haijin laws under the Hongwu Emperor, this dynasty still led seven Treasure Voyages. The eunuch Zheng He led voyages for this dynasty. For ten points, name this Chinese dynasty that preceded the Qing [ching] and is commonly known for its porcelain vases.",
        "answer": "Ming Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Ming Dynasty was established in the wake of this rebellion, which was inspired by the White Lotus Society.",
        "answer": [
          "Red Turban Rebellion",
          "Hongjin Qiyi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After participating in this event, Louis Lingg blew himself up rather than work with police. This event’s planners were sentenced by governor Richard Oglesby, though some of those rulings were later overturnedbyJohnPeterAltgeld.SomeoftheperpetratorsofthiseventsangtheMarseillaise[mar-sigh-ez] at their 1887 executions. Albert Parsons and August Spies were convicted for their roles in, for ten points, what bombing and riot at a labor rally in Chicago?",
        "answer": "Haymarket Square riot or bombing, etc."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The rally in Haymarket Square took place a day after police attacked strikers outside a factory for this manufacturing company, whose founder and namesake invented the mechanical reaper.",
        "answer": [
          "McCormick Harvesting Machine Company",
          "Cyrus McCormick"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Conflict with Native Americans",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "1876 battle where George Custer was killed in Montana.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Little Bighorn or Battle of the Greasy Grass"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lakota Sioux leader at that battle, where he joined with Crazy Horse. He was killed by American police in 1890.",
          "answer": "Sitting Bull or Thathanka Iyotake"
        },
        {
          "question": "Shawnee leader who allied with Britain during the War of 1812 and was killed at the Battle of the Thames.",
          "answer": "Tecumseh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious movement promoted by Wovoka, which sought to bring peace through the spirits of the dead.",
          "answer": "Ghost Dance movement"
        },
        {
          "question": "1670s war, named for a Wampanoag chief, in New England in which several thousand people were killed.",
          "answer": "King Philip’s War or Metacomet’s War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ottawa chief who led a 1760s rebellion against the British, besieging Fort Detroit.",
          "answer": [
            "Pontiac",
            "Obwandiyag"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1630s war that wiped out a New England tribe and included the Mystic Massacre.",
          "answer": "Pequot War"
        },
        {
          "question": "1794 battle where Little Turtle and Blue Jacket’s alliance was defeated near the Maumee River.",
          "answer": "Battle of Fallen Timbers"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Italian Wars",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City aided by Genoa and Venice in its war against Florence; it is home to a famously leaning tower.",
          "answer": "Pisa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Artist who escaped to France with his Mona Lisa after the Battle of Marignano.",
          "answer": [
            "Leonardo da Vinci",
            "either",
            "both names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Title held by the ruler of Venice.",
          "answer": "Doge"
        },
        {
          "question": "City-state led by Ludovico Sforza at the start of the Wars.",
          "answer": "Milan"
        },
        {
          "question": "League initially formed by the Papal States to oppose Venice; it names a 1508-1516 war.",
          "answer": "War of the League of Cambrai"
        },
        {
          "question": "“Warrior Pope” who organized that League and ordered the painting of the Sistine Chapel.",
          "answer": "Julius II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Decisive 1525 battle that assured Habsburg power in Italy after the Treaty of Madrid.",
          "answer": "Battle of Pavia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Genoese admiral who kicked the French out of Genoa and allied with Charles V.",
          "answer": "Andrea Doria"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Canadian Politicians",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Current Prime Minister, who protested Aung San Suu Kyi [chee]’s treatment of the Rohingya by revoking her honorary citizenship.",
          "answer": "Justin Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of the current Prime Minister, who served two terms as Prime Minister himself.",
          "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who served until 2015, the first PM from the modern Conservative Party.",
          "answer": "Stephen Harper"
        },
        {
          "question": "First prime minister of Canada, who resigned over the Pacific Scandal.",
          "answer": "John A. Macdonald"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister who resolved the Suez Canal Crisis and won a Nobel Peace Prize.",
          "answer": "Lester Pearson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prime Minister during World War II, the longest-serving PM in Canadian history.",
          "answer": "William Lyon Mackenzie King"
        },
        {
          "question": "First female Prime Minister, who served for just over four months after Brian Mulroney’s retirement.",
          "answer": "Kim Campbell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Liberal Prime Minister who opposed conscription during World War I.",
          "answer": "Wilfrid Laurier"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a film from this country, the title character is created by a clerk’s typo; that film’s score was composed by the composer of the Scythian Suite. Another composer from this country dedicated a string quartet, which opens with a (20 pts)",
        "DSCH motif, “to the victims of fascism and war;” that composer from this country also featured an “invasion” theme and a theme from his opera (10 pts)",
        "Lady Macbeth of the Mtsensk District in his Leningrad Symphony. For ten points, name this home country of Sergei Prokofiev and Dmitri Shostakovich."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Soviet Union or USSR",
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "CCCP",
        "Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this country, a siege against a native earthen fort known as the “Bat’s Nest,” Ruapekapeka. Fortifications known as pa were defended in a series of wars in this country, which contains the Bay of Islands. In this country’s settlement of Russell, the chopping down of a (20 pts)",
        "pole holding the Union Jack instigated an 1845 war in which Hone Heke [hoh-nay hay-kay] fought. Another conflict in this country began after they started to acquire (10 pts)",
        "muskets from merchants based in nearby Sydney. The Maori fought the British and each other in, for ten points, what country where the British founded cities like Wellington?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New Zealand",
        "Aotearoa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This politician was endorsed by the Suite 3505 Committee in an election in which he hammered Nelson Rockefeller’s infidelity to win his party’s nomination. This man was endorsed at the convention by the “A (20 pts)",
        "Time for Choosing” speech, given by Ronald Reagan. This man’s opponent declared that “in your (10 pts)",
        "guts, you know” that this man’s “nuts,” and criticized this man’s nuclear policy with the “Daisy” ad. For ten points, name this conservative Republican who lost in a landslide to Lyndon B. Johnson in the 1964 election."
      ],
      "answer": "Barry Morris Goldwater"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man escaped hidden in an oak tree at the Battle of Worcester. As part of the Clarendon Code passed by this man, non-Anglican Church Ministers had to stay five miles away from towns. (20 pts)",
        "Titus Oates invented a fictitious plot to kill this monarch in the Popish Plot. The Convention Parliament welcomed this king, who began the English (10 pts)",
        "Restoration. For ten points, name this king who ruled after Oliver Cromwell, who had earlier ordered the execution of his father after the English Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles II"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work, this philosopher wrote that “the self is a relation which relates itself to its own self,” and in another work he wrote “subjectivity is truth.” This thinker, who envisioned the aesthetic, ethical, and religious modes of life, had a quarrel with the Corsair satirical newspaper that led him to drop his use of (20 pts)",
        "pseudonyms. The terms “infinite resignation” and “knight of faith” were coined by this man in a work that examines (10 pts)",
        "Abraham’s binding of Isaac. For ten points, name this Danish existentialist thinker who wrote Fear and Trembling and Either/Or."
      ],
      "answer": "Soren Kierkegaard"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Cricketer John Thayer died during this event, but Milton Hershey didn’t due to an urgent need to attend to business affairs. This event, which Stanley Lord failed to respond to, is the subject of Thomas Hardy’s poem “The (20 pts)",
        "Convergence of the Twain.” The Carpathia led rescue efforts during this event, in which (10 pts)",
        "Molly Brown ordered Lifeboat 6 to look for survivors. For ten points, name this April 1912 maritime disaster involving an iceberg and an “unsinkable” ocean liner."
      ],
      "answer": "sinking of the RMS Titanic"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his role as Inspector-General, this man led a foreign army in support of Francisco Franco’s Spaniards in the Rif War. This man was appointed to his highest post after troops nearly mutinied in the wake of the failed (20 pts)",
        "Chemin des Dames offensive of Robert Nivelle. After rising to fame at the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Verdun, this man helped spearhead a government with Pierre Laval that collaborated with the Nazis. For ten points, name this war hero of World War I’s Battle of Verdun who led Vichy France."
      ],
      "answer": "Philippe Petain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Environmental work within this body of water has included the building of the Dike Kokoral and the construction of a dam across the Berg Strait. In a 1971 disaster in this body of water, a bioweapons laboratory accidentally spread weaponized (20 pts)",
        "smallpox to nearby inhabitants. The Aralkum Desert was formed in this body of water’s eastern basin, after it was (10 pts)",
        "heavily used in Soviet irrigation projects. For ten points, name this lake that lies between Kazakhstan and Uzbekistan and is rapidly shrinking."
      ],
      "answer": "Aral Sea"
    }
  ]
}